<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon concerning the punishing of malefactors. Preached at Paules Crosse, the first of October, by Charles Richardson, preacher at Saint Katharines neere the Tower of London</title>
            <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851184</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon concerning the punishing of malefactors. Preached at Paules Crosse, the first of October, by Charles Richardson, preacher at Saint Katharines neere the Tower of London</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Blower?] for William Butlar, and are to bee sold at his shoppe in the Bulwarke, neere to the Tower of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Punishment --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16448:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16448:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON concerning the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of Malefactors.</p>
            <p>Preached at Paules Croſſe, the firſt of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, by <hi>Charles Richardſon,</hi> Preacher at Saint Katharines neere the Tower <hi>of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prouerbers 20.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A wiſe King ſcattereth the wicked and cauſeth the wheele to tread ouer them.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>EX AVARITIA <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Butlar,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shoppe in the Bulwarke, neere to the Tower of London. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16448:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16448:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable</hi> Thomas <hi>Earle of Lincolne, increaſe of grace in</hi> this life, and aſsurance of glory in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am bold to preſent vnto your Honour, this plaine and homely Sermon, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to accept it as a ſincere (though a poore) teſtimonie of that moſt dutifull affection which I owe vnto you, in regard of that great kindneſſe, and vndeſerued reſpect, which your Honour hath euer borne towards me, for theſe many yeares wherin I haue beene knowne vnto you. The greateſt Monarches haue vouchſafed, to receiue poore preſents at the hands of ſuch, as were not able to afford greater gifts. And I haue had ſo long and ſo good experience of your Honours noble diſpoſition that way, as I doubt not, but this gift, how meane ſoeuer, ſhall be welcome for the affection of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. I confeſſe the Doctrine of the Sermon was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed to the Magiſtrates of this city, before whom it was preached. But becauſe I knowe, that there is as much need of reformation in the cuntry as here, eſpecially in the matter of the Sabaoth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath now aduanced your Honour to a great place of eminencie in the cuntry, I hope it will not be offenſiue, that I haue preſumed to make you
<pb facs="tcp:16448:3"/>
the Patron of it. I haue long beene a witneſſe of your Lordſhips great zeale in this reſpect. And therefore I doubt not, but as God hath now giuen you more meanes and greater power, ſo you will more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet your ſelfe to reforme thoſe groſſe abuſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is ſo much diſhonoured, and his holy name and Goſpell ſo highly prophaned. The Church of God hath had a long expectation of great good from your Honour. Now the time, by Gods mercy is come wherein you may glad the hearts of many of Gods people, by countenancing and ſupporting the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed miniſterie, and by curbing &amp; repreſſing the pride of inſolent Papiſts and Atheiſtes, who daily more and more manifeſt their impudencie againſt the truth and ſeruants of God. But I take too much vpon me. You haue beene ſo long exerciſed in godlineſſe, as I doubt not, but of your ſelfe you will bee forward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to euery good worke. I pray God bleſſe your Honour together with your moſt vertuous and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Ladie, the hopefull Lord <hi>Clinton</hi> your eldeſt, ſonne, that right noble <hi>Theophilus,</hi> and all the reſt of your worthy childen. And the Lord enlarge your heart that you may render vnto him according to the reward beſtowed vpon you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all humble dutie and ſeruice, <hi>CHARLES RICHARDSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16448:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon concerning the puniſhing <hi>of Malefactors.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalme 101.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Betimes, or earely, will I deſtroy all the wicked of the land: that I may cut off all the workers of iniquitie from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Pſalme was penned by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid,</hi> as appeareth by the title, for it is called <hi>A Pſalme of Dauid.</hi> And howſoeuer the time when it was penned bee not expreſſed: yet the <hi>Pſalme</hi> it ſelfe ſeemeth to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that he made it at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Crowne. For the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it is a ſolemne vow, wherin the <hi>Prophet</hi> bindeth himſelfe, to the performance of his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in the due ordering and gouerning of himſelfe, his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and his Kingdome. Now this vow is firſt propounded in the firſt verſe, <hi>I will ſing Mercie and Iudgement, to thee, O Lord will I ſing.</hi> And then expounded in the reſt of the <hi>Pſalme.</hi> Wherein we are to conſider, 1. What he promiſeth for himſelfe. 2. What he promiſeth concerning others. For himſelfe he promiſeth two things. 1. That he will endeauour to doe well, namely, to be an example of good vnto others, both in his publike and priuate conuerſation. 2. <hi>I will doe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16448:4"/>
wiſely, &amp;c.</hi> 2 That he will be carefull to preſerue himſelfe from euill, both from occaſions offered without, by euill obiects &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill examples. 3 <hi>I will ſet no wicked thing &amp;c.</hi> And alſo from oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions within his own heart, where he knew there was matter enough to corrupt him, though there were no outward prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation at all. 4 <hi>A froward heart &amp;c.</hi> Concerning others we are to conſider. 1 What hee promiſeth concerning thoſe that ſhould haue acceſſe to him. And becauſe he knew, that two ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons would ſeeke to inſinuate themſelues into his fauour, ſuch as were <hi>maliciouſly ſclanderous,</hi> making other mens diſgrace a ſtep for them to climbe by: &amp; ſuch as were <hi>ambitiouſly proud,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring to places of honour without deſert, therfore he ſheweth how he wil cary himſelfe towards them. 5 The one he <hi>wil deſtroy,</hi> the other he <hi>will not ſuffer,</hi> that all other wicked perſons might know, what entertainment they were to looke for at his hands. 2 What he promiſeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ſuch as he was to imploy, either as Counſellors of Eſtate, in the affaires of his kingdome, or as ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in the buſineſſes of his family: where he ſheweth. 1 What manner of perſons he wil make choice of. <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. <hi>Mine eyes ſhalbe to the faithfull of the land, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Whom he would refuſe <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. namely <hi>deceitful</hi> perſons, &amp; ſuch as <hi>tel lies.</hi> 3. What he promiſeth concerning all his Subiects &amp; his whole Kingdome in generall. And becauſe the comfort &amp; peace of good ſubiects co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in taking away the wicked, he promiſeth to ſuppres all ſuch to the vttermoſt of his power, in this verſe which I haue choſen. And thus we ſee how theſe words do depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the reſt of the <hi>Pſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, for our more orderly proceeding, we are to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider foure things in generall. 1. King <hi>Dauids iuſtice</hi> &amp; ſeuerity in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing offenders, in theſe words. <hi>I will deſtroy the wicked, &amp; cut off the workers of iniquity.</hi> Wherein we may note. 1. The action which he wil performe, ſet out in two words, <hi>deſtroy and cut off.</hi> 2. The obiect of the action, or the perſons on whom he will exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Iuſtice in this manner, namely, <hi>the wicked, &amp; the workers of Iniquity.</hi> Where the latter phraiſe expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the former. 2. His equall proceeding therein, he wil <hi>deſtroy Al the wicked &amp; cut off All the workers of iniquitie,</hi> without <hi>partialitie.</hi> 3. His <hi>diligence,</hi> he will do it <hi>betimes,</hi> without delay. 4. The end why he will doe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16448:4"/>
it <hi>betimes,</hi> without delay. 4. The end why he will doe it, that <hi>Ieruſalem the City of the Lord,</hi> may be purged from euill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wil deſtroy.</hi> This is not ſo to be vnderſtood, as if the <hi>Prophet</hi> would inflict a like puniſhment vpon all offenders, for that were iniuſtice. For as there is difference of offences, ſo there muſt be difference of puniſhments. All offenders muſt be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, but (as we ſhall ſee afterwards) euery one according to the qualitie of his falt. Our inſtruction then from hence is this; That they that are in authority,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.26</note> are bound to puniſh the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>A wiſe king ſcattereth the wick d and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the wheele ouer them.</hi> And the Lord comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>Moſes,</hi> that if any man did <hi>faſly accuſe his brother,</hi> looke what puniſhment ſoeuer hee ſhould haue ſuffered, if the accuſation had beene true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.19 21.</note> the ſame puniſhment ſhould be inflicted vpon the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer himſe fe. <hi>Yee ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l doe to him as he had thought to haue done to his brother.</hi> Thine eye ſhall haue no compaſſion: but life for life, eie for eie, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foote for foote. And in an other place, if a man by due examination of his cauſe, were found <hi>worthy to be beaten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1.2. <hi>Leui.</hi> 24.16</note> 
               <hi>the Iudge muſt cauſe him to lie downe, and to be beaten before his face.</hi> Againe, the <hi>Lord</hi> gaue a ſpecial and a ſtrict charge, that <hi>he that blaſphemed the name of the Lord ſhould be put to death: all the congregation ſhould ſtone him to death.</hi> So likewiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 5.301</note> whoſoeuer <hi>did any thing preſumptuouſly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was to be cut off from among his people.</hi> I confeſſe that men at the firſt are to be allured to obedience by rewards and other gentle courſes, but if that will not ſerue the turne, then ſeuerity muſt be vſed,<note place="margin">Praemio et paena. Solon.</note> and puniſhments muſt be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Whereupon the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid, hat the common wealth was vpheld by two things, namely by <hi>rewards and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> But howſoeuer, if there be not ſeuerity to keepe men in awe, the common wealth cannot be well gouerned. And therefore it was the commandement of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> vnto <hi>Ezra,</hi> that <hi>whoſoeuer would not doe the law of his God, and the Kings law, he ſhould haue iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment &amp;c.</hi> And there are many reaſons which may further confirme the truth of this point. For firſt if pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhment be not inflicted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offenders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much euill and hurt will follow thereupon as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, firſt of all the offender himſefe, and others alſo are animated
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16448:5"/>
and encouraged in their lewde courſes: <hi>Their hands are ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hened that they cannot returne from their wickedneſſe,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith in another ſence.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.14.</note> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Maxima pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi ille cebra impunitatis ſpes. Cic. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> The greateſt prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that can bee, is hope of impunitie. Neither is any greater cauſe of euill, then libertie to doe euill. Becauſe <hi>Eli</hi> would not correct his ſonnes, but rather ſtroked their heads when they did amiſſe, therefore they behaued themſelues ſo vilely in their places, as by reaſon of their ſinne, <hi>men abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Offering of the Lord.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſo coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>Adoniah, as he would not diſpleaſe him from his Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17 23.24. 1. <hi>Ki.</hi> 1.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Why haſt thou done ſo?</hi> Therefore there was none more ready to take the Crowne from his Fathers head. As it is in priuate families, ſo it is in Common-wealthes, when men are not puniſhed according to their deſerts, they become more diſſolute. And therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith well,<note n="b" place="margin">Nulla maio mali c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſa, quam licentia mali. Caſ.</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Impunitas incuriae ſobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, inſolen iae mater, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſionum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut. ix. Ber. de Conſid. l. 3.</note> Impunitie is the brood of careleſneſſe, the mother of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie, the nurſe of tranſgreſſions.<note n="c" place="margin">Ad pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum p aecipi tes f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, qui impune pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. Tract. 1. contra De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metr. Alex ab Alex. lib. 3 cap. 5.<hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.5.6 <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 8.11.</note> And <hi>Cyprian,</hi> They that ſinne without controlement, runne headlong to ſinne. Impunitie is the fewell, that feedeth the fury of diſſolute and vnbridled perſons. And therefore, it was wiſely prouided by the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that their Magiſtrates ſhould neuer come in publike without their Officers, to beare halberds and rods before them, for the terror of thoſe that ſhould offend. As wicked men deale with Almightie God, ſo doe they deale with the Magiſtrate his Deputie. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of the wicked, that becauſe <hi>his wayes alwayes proſper, and the Iudgements of God are out of his ſight, therefore he ſaith in his heart, I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be moued, nor be in danger,</hi> and, <hi>God hath forgotten, he hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth away his face, and will neuer ſee.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the children of men is fully ſet in them to doe euill.</hi> So when the Magiſtrate is negligent in puniſhing offenders, they and others are more emboldened to ſinne. We read in the booke of Iudges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 17 6 <hi>&amp;</hi> 18 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21 25.</note> of many grieuous abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, that were committed among the Iſraelites as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Micahs</hi> making of a grauen and a molten Image, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating
<pb facs="tcp:16448:5"/>
of a Leuite for Idolatrous ſeruice: the Danites ſpoyling their brethren by force of Armes, and ſacking of their cities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the horrible abuſe offered to the Leuites wife &amp;c. And the cauſe of all is ſaid to be this <hi>In thoſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael</hi> there was no Magiſtrate nor Law to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, <hi>but euery man did that which was good in his owne eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, when men are ſuffered to tranſgreſſe without puniſhment, the wrath of God is prouoked, and publike calamities are pulled downe vpon the land. The Lord tolde the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that if blood were ſhed in the land, and the murderer not put to death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 35.33</note> the <hi>land was defiled</hi> and made lyable to Gods heauie diſpleaſure. When <hi>Ahab</hi> charged the <hi>Prophet Elijah,</hi> that he was the man that <hi>troubled Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.18.</note> and cauſed that great famine that was in the land: he anſwered boldly, <hi>That it was he and his Fathers houſe that troubled Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> in that he ſuffered ſo much Idolatry to be vnpuniſhed. When <hi>Achan</hi> had ſtollen the <hi>conſecrated thing,</hi> the wrath of the Lord was ſo kindled againſt all the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.11.12.</note> that they could not ſtand, but were diſcomfited before their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord threatned, that <hi>he would be no more with them, vnleſſe they deſtroyed that perſon from among them.</hi> When that villany was committed vpon the <hi>Leuites Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine</hi> and the <hi>Beniamites</hi> would not deliuer thoſe wicked men that had done it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20.12.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that they might be put to death to put away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from Iſrael,</hi> the Lord ſtirred vp the reſt of their brethren to make war e againſt them, till the whole Tribe was almoſt deſtroyed.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1.</note> So long as the murder committed by <hi>Saul</hi> vpon the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> was vnpuniſhed, the Lord ſent a grieuous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vpon the land of <hi>Iſrael three yeares together.</hi> And whiles <hi>Ionah,</hi> that had fl d from the pr ſence of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah.</hi> 1.4.</note> was in the Shippe, a great winde and a mightie Tempoſt, raiſed by the Lord purſued the Ship, that it <hi>was like to be broken,</hi> and all the <hi>Marriners</hi> in danger of drowning. On the contrary ſide, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is executed vpon wicked doers, the wrath of God is turned away, and he is pacified and appeaſed.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16448:6"/>
When the <hi>wrath of Lord was kindled againſt Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 25.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he had ioined himſelfe to Baal-Peor:</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Moſes to take all the heads of the people, and hang them vp before the Lord againſt the ſunne, that the indignation of the Lords wrath might be turned from Iſrael.</hi> And according, when <hi>Phinehas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 106.30.</note> in an holy zeale, had thruſt through the <hi>man of Iſrael</hi> and the <hi>Midianitiſh woman</hi> with a ſpeare, <hi>the plague ceaſed from the children of Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> relating the ſame ſtorie ſaid, that <hi>Phinehas ſtood vp and executed iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the plague was ſtaied.</hi> When <hi>Achan</hi> and all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed vnto him were ſtoned vnto death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.25.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>tot.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Lord turned from his fierie wrath againſt Iſrael,</hi> ſo that whereas before their enemies chaſed them and ſmote them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah.</hi> 1, 15</note> now they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued many great and famous victories. When <hi>Ionah</hi> was once caſt into the ſea,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.9.14.</note> the <hi>ſea preſently ceaſed from her raging.</hi> When the <hi>ſeauen ſons of Saul</hi> were hanged vp <hi>in Gibea of Saul</hi> as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> requited <hi>God was then appeaſed with the land</hi> And in a word,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.40.45.</note> when <hi>Eliah</hi> had ſlaine the <hi>fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hundred faulſe Prophets</hi> &amp; idolatrous prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> whereas before there had beene neither <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw nor raine</hi> for a long time, the Lord preſently ſent raine in abundance, whereby the former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ceaſed. And therefore, if Magiſtrates deſire, either to preuent the iudgements that are threatned, or hang ouer the land, or to remoue thoſe that are already inflicted, they muſt carefully looke to the puniſhing of ſuch as by their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe <hi>increaſe the wrath of God vpon the land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, where wicked men eſcape vnpuniſhed, yea not onely ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.28 <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.2.</note> but (as oft it falleth out) are exalted, there the good are grieued and diſcouraged: yea, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, they are conſtrained <hi>to hide themſelues and to ſigh and mourne</hi> for ſorrow. It is a true ſaying,<note n="a" place="margin">Bonis nocet qui malis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</note> he hurteth the good, that ſpareth them that are euill. The Apoſtle inſinuateth, that <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> ought to prouide, that thoſe that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them <hi>may leade a quiet and a peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſtie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> But it cannot bee, that men ſhould liue peaceably and quietly, vnleſſe wicked men by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16448:6"/>
be reſtrained and kept in awe, for they will be ſo inſolent, as a man of a quiet diſpoſition cannot dwell by them; but the more he ſhall <hi>ſeeke for peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.7.</note> the more will <hi>they be bent to warre,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of his enemies. Neither is it poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible that <hi>godlineſſe and honeſtie</hi> ſhould flouriſh where wicked perſons are vncontrouled. For as weedes let grow doe ouertoppe the good corne, and choake it: ſo lewd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons left at liberty, hinder the growth of pietie and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
            <p>And as all theſe euils doe follow vpon the neglect of this duetie: ſo on the contrary ſide, much good will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounde to the commonwealth, where it is carefully and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently put in practiſe. As firſt of all, the party delinquent is by this meanes reformed, and brought to liue in better order. For that that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of children, is true alſo of elder perſons, that <hi>fooliſhneſſe is bound in their heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>but the rod of correction ſhall driue it away from them.</hi> And therefore, he ſaith in another place.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.30.</note> 
               <hi>The blewneſſe of the wound ſerueth to purge the euill, and the ſtripes within the bowels of the belly.</hi> And hereof we haue an example in the inceſtuous perſon, who being excommunicated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto Satan, was thereby brought to ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and repentance,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6.7</note> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> to receiue him againe into the boſome of the Church, <hi>leaſt he ſhould be ſwallowed vp of ouermuch heauineſſe.</hi> And many amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, that had it not beene for correction, they had neuer come to good. But if it be ſo, as ſometimes we ſee it commeth to paſſe, that a man is ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in euill, as that by puniſhment he cannot be quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed: yet he is ſo curbed and kept in awe, as he dare not ſinne ſo boldly as otherwiſe he would.<note n="b" place="margin">Meliores ſunt quos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigit amor, ſed plu es quos co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>igit timor</note> For howſoeuer it bee true, that the better ſort are directed by loue, yet the greater ſort are corrected by feare.<note n="c" place="margin">Oderunt peccare mali formidine pocnae.</note> And euen the worſt that are, will abſtaine from euill for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the puniſhment of malefactors, others
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16448:7"/>
will be admoniſhed to walke more warily. The Lord tolde <hi>Moſes</hi> that when due puniſhment ſhould be inflicted vpon the falſe witneſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 19.19 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.21</note> 
               <hi>The reſt ſhould heare and feare, and ſhould henceforth commit no more any ſuch wickedneſſe among them.</hi> And commaundement is giuen, that the ſtubborne and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Sonne ſhould be ſtoned with ſtones, <hi>that all Iſrael may heare it and feare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20 <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.11.</note> And the Apoſtle chargeth <hi>Timotheus, to rebuke them openly that ſinne, that the reſt alſo may feare.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith expreſly, that <hi>when a Scorner is puniſhed, the ſimple will be wiſe.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Animaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones quo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriores, eo plus ad exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datione inque proficiunt. Sen. de ira. l 3.</note> And doubtleſſe, publicke chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and puniſhments are very profitable for the example and amendment of others.<note n="b" place="margin">Vt fulnuna pâncorum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculo cadunt, omi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu. ſic ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiones terrent latius quam nocent.</note> For as the Thunderbolt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with the danger of a few, but with the feare of all: ſo the terror of puniſhments teacheth further then the ſmart.<note n="c" place="margin">Metus ad omnes, poena ad paucos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit. Cic. pro A Cluentio. Punitis malis f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iunt iuſti at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiores, et Chryſoſt. in Pſ. 7.</note> For the feare is extended to all men, but the puniſhment to a few. To this purpoſe <hi>Chryſoſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath a good ſaying. <hi>(d)</hi> When the euill are puniſhed, ſaith he the righteous are made more carefull. For as a ſound man when he ſeeth one that is wounded either feared or launced, is made more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of his owne health: ſo when a man ſeeth a malefactor brought to deſerued puniſhment, he is admoniſhed to take heede of ſuch courſes. It was a true ſaying in the generall of the <hi>Proconſul</hi> to <hi>Cyprian</hi> at his Martyrdome, though ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to him in particuler<note n="e" place="margin">In ſanguine tuo caeteri diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent diſcipli.</note> In thy blood the reſt wil learne diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Luſt of all, when as by due execution of Iuſtice diſſolute perſons are cut off, the whole bodie of the Common-wealth is preſerued from infection<note n="f" place="margin">Cic. in M. Anton. Phil. 8.</note> As in a found body, if there be any thing that endangereth the reſt of the body, we ſuffer it be feared and cut, that ſome one me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r may rather pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh then the whole body: ſo in the body of the Common-wealth, that the whole may be preſerued, let all that is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full be cut off.<note n="g" place="margin">Cuncta pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tentand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um dicab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le vulnus Enſe reſidendum, ne pars ſincera trahatu. Ouid Metam lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> All oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r courſes (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the <hi>Poet</hi> ſaid are firſt to be taken; and all other meanes to be vſed, but if the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be incurerable, it muſt be cut off, that the found parts be not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16448:7"/>
infected.<note n="a" place="margin">Truncatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus, vt l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceat reliquis ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum viuere membris. Claudian.</note> And ſometimes we cut off a ioynt, that the reſt of the members may be without feare.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee the neceſſity of the performance of this duety: Now for the better effecting thereof, it is neceſſary that good <hi>Lawes</hi> be eſtabliſhed, and that they bee carefully and duely executed. It cannot be denied, but that we haue in this kingdome as good and as wholeſome Lawes, as any nation in Chriſtendome, onely it is to be lamented that the execution of them is ſo much neglected. It were to be wiſhed that they that haue authority in this caſe, would be carefull, that the Lawes made with ſo good aduice, and ſo great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, may not be like an abor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue fruit, dead as ſoone as they are borne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawe,</hi> though neuer ſo excellent, without execution,<note place="margin">Leges vel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuione vel contemptu pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, ſecuri orem lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uni fecere. Cor. Tacit. Annal. lib. 3. 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.4</note> are but like a body without a ſoule, like a ſword that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the ſheath, and like a medicine that is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. <hi>b</hi> And as one ſaith well, when the Lawes are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, either by forgetfulneſſe or contempt, they make men more ſecure and riotous. Now the Lawes will neuer bee well executed, nor abuſes reformed, vnleſſe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, as much as lyeth in him, ſee it done with his owne eies. There is a worthy preſident thereof in good <hi>Ioſiah</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that when he began to root out <hi>idolatry, they brake downe in his fight the Altars of Baalim, and cut downe the Images that were vpon them.</hi> Yea <hi>he went throughout all the land of Iſraell, to deſtroy the Altars, and the groues, and to breake and ſtampe to powder the images, &amp;c. and then retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Ieruſalem:</hi> hee would not truſt his officers with the buſineſſe, but ſaw it done himſelfe.<note n="c" place="margin">Sabel. Enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. 5. lib. 4.</note> When the <hi>Romanes</hi> had nominated <hi>Titus Manlius Torquatus</hi> to be <hi>Conſul,</hi> he aleadging the infirmity of his eyes, refuſed the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſaid, he ſhould bring in a very euill and pernitious example,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if he ſhould vndertake to gouern the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth with other mens eies. And therefore <hi>Homer</hi> requireth of a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> that he haue eies <hi>before and behinde</hi> that he may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16448:8"/>
looke euery way. Otherwiſe, if they referre all to vnder of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, who it may be, either loue the ſinne themſelues, or elſe are many times corrupted with bribes, they ſhall eaſily be deceiued.</p>
            <p>This doctrine doth ſerue: firſt, for the reproofe of all thoſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note> that being in authority, are not carefull to puniſh diſordered perſons. As there are many that are too indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and winke too much at thoſe that deſerue puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Some becauſe they are guilty themſelues, cannot with any face puniſh ſinne in others. If the Magiſtrate be a ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or a drankard, or a whore-maiſter, or a prophaner of the Sabboath, how can he ſet himſelfe to puniſh theſe vices in other men? Others, againe there are, that forbeare to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh malefactors, becauſe they would be counted pittifull and mercifull men, not remembring the old prouerbe, that <hi>fooliſh pittie wareth the citie.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Multi ibi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men crudelita tis imponunt etc Auguſt de bono diſcipl.</note> Many ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> call that cruelty, when for loue of diſcipline, the fault com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted is reuenged by the puniſhments of the offender: whereas the ſentence of him that puniſheth, ſatisfieth the law, and redoundeth to the good, not onely of them that are preſent, but euen of them alſo that are yet vnborne.<note n="c" place="margin">Seueritas v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate publica rependitur. Cor. Tac: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal lib. 14.</note> So that, the ſeueritie that is vſed in this caſe, is recompenced with the publike benefits.<note n="d" place="margin">Maluit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitius crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis in animad. vertendo, quam in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mittando diſſolutus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri. Cic. in ver. lib. 5. <hi>Num.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.27.28. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.5 6.7.8.</note> It is ſaid of <hi>Domitius,</hi> that he had rather ſeeme cruell in puniſhing, then diſſolute in ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <hi>Moſes was a very meeke man, aboue all that were vpon the earth:</hi> and yet he batheth his hands in the blood of his brethren, when they had diſhonoured God, by making and worſhiping the golden calfe. And <hi>Dauid</hi> that was al his life of ſo milde a diſpoſition, and ſo tender hearted, that when opportunity was offered him twice, he would not lay his hands vpon <hi>Saul</hi> though he were his mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, yea his heart did ſmite him, when he had but <hi>cut off the lap of his garment,</hi> yet at his death hee maketh a bloody will, and chargeth <hi>Solomon</hi> that hee ſhould cauſe <hi>the gray head of Ioab and Shemei to goe to the graue with blood.</hi> Both of them by this cruelty ſanctified their heads, whiles they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16448:8"/>
executed the vengeance committed vnto them by God which otherwiſe, by ſparing they ſhould haue pollunted.<note place="margin">Caluin inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 20. ſect. 10. <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.29</note> As <hi>Moſes</hi> bad the <hi>Iſaelites concecrate their hands to the Lord, euery man vpon his ſonne and vpon his brother.</hi> Others yet there be, that vſe too much conniuencie in this caſe, becauſe they would be thought to be quiet and peaceable. And this is commonly the fault of ſuch as he annuall Magiſtrates, who becauſe they are not long to continue in place of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, are loath to be too buſie and too medling for their time. They deſire euery bodies good word, let them that come after them, looke to the reformation of things that are amiſſe. But they forget in the meane while the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> exhortation, who ſaith, <hi>follow peace with all men and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> So farre as <hi>peace</hi> may ſtand with <hi>holineſſet</hi> ſo farre a man ſhould labour to be peaceable, but if it cannot ſtand with holineſſe <hi>warre</hi> is to be preferred before ſuch <hi>peace.</hi> When <hi>Iehoram asked Iehu, Is it peace Iehu?</hi> he anſweted, <hi>What peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 9.22</note> 
               <hi>whiles the whoredomes of thy mother Iezebel, and her witchcrafts are great in number?</hi> So ſhould euery godly <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> reſolue in a holy zeale, neuer to be at peace with wicked perſons, ſo long as their ſinnes are vnpuniſhed. Laſt of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that are ready to ſpeake and write for leaude perſons, to reſcue them, as it were from, the hand and ſtroake of the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> As we ſee by common experience, that there is none ſo vile, but one or other will intreate for him, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that fauour or credite which they haue with men of authoritie, to the countenancing and bolſtering vp of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, Well, let all theſe perſons know, that if by any of theſe meanes they ſubduce a malefactor from deſerued puniſhment, they make themſelues guilty of his ſinne. It is a true ſaying,<note n="a" place="margin">Iudex dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natu, cum no cens abſolui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> the Iudge is condemned when the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is abſolued.<note n="b" place="margin">qui non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat peccare cum potest iubet Sen. <hi>Prou.</hi> 24.24 <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.15.</note> And hee that doth not reſtraine a man, when it is in his power, doth command him to ſinne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, and the multitude ſhall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16448:9"/>
abhorre him.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Hee that iuſtifieth the wicked is abhomination to the Lord</hi> Giuing vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand, that whereas they thinke by this meanes, to winn the fauour and eſtimation of men, they make themſelues odious both to God and all good men. Beſides the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture maketh it cleare and euident, that by this remiſſeneſſe they make themſelues lyable to the wrath of God. When the Lord ſent <hi>Saul</hi> in expedition againſt the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and gaue him a charge <hi>to ſmite them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3</note> 
               <hi>and to deſtroy all that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto them, and to haue no compaſsion on them, but to ſtay both man and woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> 
               <hi>infant and ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling, &amp;c.</hi> And he contrary to this charge, <hi>tooke A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag the King aliue, Samuel</hi> was ſent to tell him,<note place="margin">23.</note> that <hi>becauſe he had in that manner caſt away the word of the Lord, the Lord had caſt him away from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing K ng.</hi> And whereas <hi>Ahab</hi> had by Gods aſsiſtance diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited <hi>Benhadad</hi> the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> and had not put him to death,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 20.42.</note> but vpon certaine conditions had let him goe, a <hi>Prophet</hi> was ſent vnto him with this meſſage. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt let goe out of thine hand a man whom I appointed to die, thy lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall goe for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and wicked perſons by the law of God are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die, the Lord hath giuen <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> a charge to that purpoſe, if therefore they, for fooliſh pity, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect let them eſcape, they may iuſtly feare, that Gods hand will be vpon themſelues. And many times we ſee by experience, that a wicked wretch reſerued from due puniſhment, proueth a continuall vexation to him that hath ſpared him. As the nations that inhabited the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> being not caſt out and deſtroyed by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Iud</hi> 2.3.</note> as God had commanded them, were made by the iuſt iudgement of God, <hi>A ſnare and deſtruction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and a whippe on their ſides, and a thorne in their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this doctrine doth ſerue to admoniſh all that are in authoritie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> to ſet themſelues with care and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to performe this duetie. The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt <hi>not beare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16448:9"/>
the ſword for naught,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, he muſt not be like a <hi>Scarre-Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> to let the birds picke ſtrawes out of his noſe, but he muſt draw the ſword that God hath put in his hand, to cut off ſuch as will not otherwiſe bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. And herein he muſt ſpare none. If a pecuniary m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be to be inflicted,<note n="a" place="margin">qui non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be in ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at in corpore.</note> hee that hath it not in his purſe, let him pay it on his skinne. If he deſerue a corporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, the Magiſtrate muſt not omit it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 19.21</note> 
               <hi>his eye muſt haue no compaſsion.</hi> And herein he hath the example of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> who comming to driue the <hi>buyers and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers out of the Temple,</hi> doth not prepare his eares to heare them, but a <hi>whippe</hi> to ſcourge them.<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. lib. 1.</note> Hee maketh no words, nor receiueth any anſwere, for he ſitteth not as a Iudge, but purſueth them as a reuenger. The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt doe likewiſe, his zeale muſt bee inflamed againſt the generall impudency of the times, he muſt make vngodly perſons afraide of his countenance, ſo as they ſhall not dare to come in his ſight. As <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, that when he was in proſperitie, his authoritie did ſo terrifie the wicked of his time, that they durſt not ſhew their heads, <hi>they were chaſed from among men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 30.3.4.5.6.</note> and were conſtrained to <hi>flee into wilderneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and there to <hi>hide themſelues in ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of riuers, and holes of the earth, and rockes,</hi> where <hi>they cut vp nettles by the buſhes, and the iuriper rootes were their meate.</hi> Yea the leaſt ſinne that is muſt not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape vnpuniſhed. We ſee by experience, that many times a little itch turneth to a filthie leproſie, that ſpreadeth it ſelfe ouer the whole body: ſo a maſſe of euill doth often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe of a ſmall beginning. A graine of poyſon is enough to take away a mans life, and the leaſt euill is ſufficient to ſpoile a whole citie.<note place="margin">Caſus in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And therefore in euils we are not to reſpect the waight of them, but the danger, not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but the contagiouſneſſe. The leaſt mote of euill, as one ſaith, is not to be neglected. The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt take heede that by the name of a little eui l, hee bee not dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with this <hi>paralogiſme,</hi> forgiue this, this is but a ſmall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16448:10"/>
falt, and forgiue this, this is but a ſmall fault, and ſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fault ſhall be accounted ſmall, and none ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As in a diſeaſed body, <hi>Phiſitians</hi> labour to leaue no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humour, that may endanger the body: ſo the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> muſt leaue nothing in the common-wealth, that may be hurtfull to it.<note n="a" place="margin">Part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſaepe ſcin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lla neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecta magnum excitauit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendium. Curt. lib. 6.</note> A little ſparke not regarded, hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times raiſed a great f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re: ſo a little euill neglected, hath often turned to a great miſchife. But as the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt puniſh all ſinne in generall, ſo more eſpecially ſuch as make moſt to the diſhonour of God, as blaſphemous ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, whoredome, profanation of the <hi>Sabboath,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Now herein many <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are much to blame. They are ſeuere enough to puniſh the leaſt diſgrace that is offered to their owne perſons. But let God be neuer ſo much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and his <hi>Sabboathes</hi> neuer ſo greatly polluted, there are but a few that doe regard i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I confeſſe there hath beene a good beginning made this laſt yeare, for the reformation of the Sabboath. The right honourable the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> that now is, and the other officers that aſsiſted him, haue taken great paines in reſtraining the abuſes and diſorders, that are in <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Alehouſes</hi> on that day. I wiſh the like care may be continued in the next yeare. And therefore I would intreate the <hi>Lord Elect</hi> that is to ſucceede, that the example of thoſe that haue gone before him may encourage him to vndertake this good worke of the Lord. He ſhall finde it an eaſier matter then it was before, becauſe the yee are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready well broken to his hands, vngodlineſſe is already well curbed, it were pittie that by any future remiſſeneſſe, it ſhould get head againe. And let me exhort the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> that are newly come in place: that as they are famous in this reſpect, that they are brothers by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (a thing ſeldome or neuer ſeene before in this cittie) ſo alſo they would ioine together in brotherly affection, that with one heart and one hand they may ſet themſelues, to the vttermoſt of their authoritie, to puniſh and roote out all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſons. So ſhall they transferre a bleſſed memory of their names to all poſteritie, and no doubt the Lord will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16448:10"/>
remember them in goodneſſe for the ſame.</p>
            <p>There is another ſort of wicked perſons, that deſerue to be ſeuerely pun ſhed. And they are thoſe which foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people call wiſe men and wiſe women: but indeede are wiſards and ſorce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes of the diuell, that take vpon them by the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of the diuell to helpe men to things that are l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt or ſtoine. Theſe are ſo odious in the ſight of God, as hee can by no mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es endure them. <hi>Let none be found among you</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>that vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th witchcra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r is a r garder of times or a ſorcerer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu</hi> 18 10 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er or that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>eth with ſpirits, or a ſooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth counſel of the dead For all that doe ſuch things, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nation vnto the Lord.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath giuen expreſſe commandement, that they ſhall bee put to death. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a witch,</hi> (and and theſe vpon the point are no better <hi>to liue.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>If a man or woman haue a ſpirit of diuination,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo</hi> 22.18 <hi>Leui.</hi> 20.27</note> 
               <hi>or ſoo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doubtleſſe theſe haue they ſhall die the death, they ſhall ſtone them to death, their blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſhall be vpon them.</hi> An as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of <hi>idols that all that truſt in them are like vnto them?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.8</note> So all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto theſe inſtruments of the diuell, are euery w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt as abomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able to God as themſelues are. And therefore hee doth preciſely co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all ſuch pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu</hi> 19.31.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not regard them that work with ſpirits neither ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſayers: ye ſhall not ſeeke to t em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be defiled by them I am the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o d your God.</hi> And in another p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>If any turne af er ſuch as worke with ſpirits and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſooth ſayers to goe a who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing after them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>then will I ſet my face againſt that man, and will cut him off from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g his people.</hi> And how ſeuerely th s threatning was execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in two fearefull examples. The one is of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who being <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt with a fall out of a window,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.2 3.4.16.1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> ſent meſſengers to enquire of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zebub the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kron,</hi> that is of the diuell, to ſee whether he ſhould recouer of his diſeaſe or no. But the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16448:11"/>
Lord ſent him word by his meſſengers, and after cauſed the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> to tell him to his face, that becauſe he had enquired of Baal zebub, as if there had beene no God in Iſraell, therefore hee ſhould not <hi>come downe off the bed, on which hee was gone vp, but ſhould dye the death.</hi> And it came to paſſe accordingly. The other is of <hi>Saul</hi> who, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Scripture ſaith in plaine tearmes;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 10.13 14.</note> 
               <hi>died for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, which hee committed againſt the Lord, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai ſt the word of the Lord which hee kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not, and becauſe hee ſought and asked counſell of one that had a familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and asked not of the Lord therefore he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſlew him, &amp;c.</hi> Seeing then this practiſe is ſo damnable, and ſo much diſpleaſing vnto Go, it ſhall be a worke worthy the care of a <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate,</hi> by due puniſhment to reſtraine the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all other, there are none that doe ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be pu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed with all ſeueritie, as our traiterous Pap ſts tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> viperous brood, who being nouriſhed in our boſomes doe moſt vnnaturally ſeeke to eate out our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w ls.<note n="a" place="margin">Cic. in Cat. 4</note> They that haue ſo often ſought by horrible conſpiracies to take away a l our liues, are not worthy for one moment to enioy the benefit of their liues: much leſſe are they worthy to partake in the priuiledge of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes. It was the Oratours rule againſt <hi>Cataline;</hi> and it holdeth in all ſuch as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is that<note n="b" place="margin">qui reipub. hoſtis eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ciuis ſte null modo poteſt, ibid.</note> hee that is an enemy to the Common-wea th cannot by any meanes be a true ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect. Neither ſhall our Magiſt ates neede to feare to be counted cruell in puniſhing ſuch ſeditious and rebellious perſons as theſe.</p>
            <p>Nay rather, if they bee moſt ſeuere in this caſe, they ſhall bee thought mercifull: but if they bee remiſſe and negligent, they ſhall bee ſubiect to the imputation of extreame crueltie to their Country and Common-wealth. Now among theſe, there are none to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16448:11"/>
againſt with more extremity, then their <hi>Prieſts and Ieſuites,</hi> the ringleaders of villeny. But I giue them a wrong name: they deſerue rather to be called <hi>Iudaſites,</hi> then <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites,</hi> for they are farre more like to <hi>Iudas,</hi> then to <hi>Ieſus:</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid of ſome ſuch as they are<note n="c" place="margin">Non poteſt eſſe cum chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto qui imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Iudae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe quam Chriſti. ſerm. 6. de orat do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica.</note> he cannot belong to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that had rather imitate <hi>Iudas</hi> then <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Their Church hath long delighted in barbarous cruelty<note n="d" place="margin">Crudelibus morſibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta et Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anorum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine opina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Optat. lib. 2 <hi>Reuel</hi> 17.6. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.8.9.</note> it hath beene fed with cruell bits, and fatted with the blood of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> It is that <hi>ſcarlet coloured whore which the Apoſtle Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>is drunken with the blood of Saints &amp; with the blood of the Martyres of Ieſus,</hi> and that without any reſpect either of ſexe or of age not ſparing the infant in the mothers belly And therefore, it were to be wiſhed, that <hi>Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> according to Gods commandement <hi>would reward them as they haue rewarded vs, and giue them double, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their workes: and in the cup that they haue filled to vs fill</hi> them double. They are the children <hi>of Babel worthy to be deſtroyed</hi> (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith.) And therefore, <hi>Bleſſed ſhall he be that rewardeth them at they haue ſerued vs. Bleſſed ſhall he be that taketh their children, and daſheth them againſt the ſtones.</hi> Still theſe wretches doe thirſt for blood, ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they might once be ſatisfied: but in that ſort as <hi>Queene Tomyris</hi> dealt with blood thirſtie <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who hauing ouercome him in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, cauſed his head to be cut off and caſt into a barrell of blood prouided for the purpoſe; and then inſulting ouer him ſaid.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go te ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine ſaturabo Herodotan Clio.</p>
                  <p>Sic pereant et qui moliti ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia per gunt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.6.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>I will giue thee blood thy belly full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloued, we haue cauſe to giue great thankes to almighty God, who hath ſo often deliued vs from thoſe apparant miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch efes, which they had intended a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt vs. <hi>The Lord hath not giuen vs ouer for a pray vnto their teeth,</hi> We may truely ſay to the glory of our God that preſerueth vs. <hi>Our ſoule is eſcaped euen us a bird out of the ſnare of the foulers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Cic in Cati. 1</note> 
               <hi>the ſnare is broken and we are deliuered.</hi> Suffer not, I beſeech you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not the ſafety of the land and kingdome to be any more endangered by their meanes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 8.20.21.</note> But you that haue authority in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, you that haue ſtrength in your hands, <hi>riſe and fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16448:12"/>
them, as <hi>Gedeon</hi> did vpon <hi>Zebah</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna,</hi> wee that be Miniſters may crie out againſt them, and inferiour Magiſtrates may ſeeke to puniſh them, and both be laughed to ſcorne for our paines. It is you that haue greater power, that muſt doe the deede.<note place="margin">A Gell. lib. 7. cap. 3.</note> Strike therefore, and ſtrike home, that both <hi>head and taile,</hi> both the great <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour <hi>Prieſts</hi> may be cut off before they deuiſe any more treaſon. It is good pollicie, not to recompence benefits and good turnes, before they be performed and done: but is a point of great folly not to preuent intended villenies, but to linger and ſtay till they be committed, and then to thinke to puniſh them, when the miſchiefe that is done cannot be vndone. How it commeth to paſſe I know not, but the truth is they haue too much liberty. Euen thoſe of them that be in priſon, are little reſtrained by their impriſonment. They haue the Maſſes as ordinarie and as common, and there is as great reſort of many ſorts of people to them, whom they ſeduce and peruert, as if they were in their owne houſes, yea they can at their pleaſure goe abroade all the citie ouer. And yet they are not aſhamed to crie out of heard and cruell v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that they are like to bee famiſhed, and I know not what. Indeede I am ſorrie for their heauineſſe. He that ſhall looke on the cheekes of many of them, will thinke they are better fedde then taught. They know well enough, that in <hi>Queeene Marias time,</hi> the poore ſeruants and <hi>Martyres</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> endured other manner of perſecution at their hands. They were mannacled and fettered, and kept in the ſtockes night and day,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.27.</note> yea not onely their feete, but their neckes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. They were <hi>fed with the bread of affliction, and the water of affliction.</hi> Theſe men walke vp and downe in their brauerie, and eate of all the dainties that may be, and yet are not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Well let me exhort thoſe that be in authoritie, that if they will not <hi>hung them vp vnto the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.6</note> as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſaid of <hi>Sauls ſonnes,</hi> (which yet I am perſwaded would be as acceptable a ſacrifice to God as that was, and as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a ſpectacle to all God people) yet they would tie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16448:12"/>
them ſhorter, and make their impriſonment a reſtraint indeede, that they may not haue ſo much liberty to doe miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will obiect. Will you then deny all mercy vnto thoſe that doe offend. No by no meanes. I know that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>The Kings throne ſhall be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with mercy.</hi> I would not haue the ſeate of Iuſtice to be<note n="a" place="margin">Reorum ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 3. cap. 5.</note> the rocke of malefactors, as they ſaid of the <hi>tribunal</hi> of <hi>Caſsius.</hi> I hate the cruelty of <hi>Draco,</hi> who puniſhed the lighteſt and ſmalleſt offence with death, and therefore was ſaid <hi>to write his lawes not with incke but with blood.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">M lum eſt delectari ſono catenarum Sen de clement. li. 1. cap. vlt.</note> I hold it a filthy thing for a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to delight (as one ſaith) in the ratling of chaines and fetters, as a carter that is neuer well but when he heares the laſhing of his whippe. But as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the beginning of this <hi>Pſalme. I will ſing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iudgement:</hi> ſo I would haue all thoſe that are to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh offenders, to temper mercy and iuſtice together,<note n="c" place="margin">Vt non faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, aut ſeue ritas amorem minuat. Cor. Tac. in vita Iul Agric.</note> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Milis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas non diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta clemen ia Plin Sec. in panegyr.</note> that too much leuitie doe not derogate from their authority, nor too much ſeueritie doe not diminiſh their loue. They<note n="d" place="margin">Tam omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ignoſcere crudelitas eſt quam nulli. Sen. de cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. l. 1 c. 2. a Poteſt poena diluta exigi, non poteſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acta renocari. Sen. de ira. l. 2. Sen de cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment l. 1.</note> muſt vſe a milde ſeueritie, and not a diſſolute clemencie, as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaid of <hi>Tragane</hi> the <hi>Emperour.</hi> As they muſt not ſhew mercie hand ouer head, ſo they muſt not denie mercie to all. <hi>e</hi> For it is as great cruelty to ſhew mercy to all, as to none. And therefore, to the end that the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> may carrie himſelfe vprightly in this caſe, there are diuerſe cauſions to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Firſt of all, they muſt not be too headlong, nor too haſtie in inflicting puniſhment. All other meanes, as we haue ſaid before, muſt be vſed, and if they be deſpiſed and contemned, then at the laſt they muſt come to puniſhment. It was a good ſaying of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ne ſuperet medicina mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> A puniſhment that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, may be exacted: but if it be once inflicted, it cannot be recalled. Secondly, they muſt labour by ſmaller &amp; lighter pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments to peruent greater. They muſt not come to capitall puniſhments at the firſt, vnleſſe the feare of future euill be greater then the preſent. Death is the laſt puniſhment, and therefore there is none will inflict it, but he that hath ſpent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16448:13"/>
all his other remedies. Thirdly, they muſt puniſh in equity and due proportion, according to the quality of the offence.<note n="a" place="margin">Neſuperet medicina mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> The medicine muſt exceede me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure. And this was the commandement of the Lord himſelfe, that if a wicked man were found worthy to be beaten, the Iudge ſhould cauſe him to lie downe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.2.</note> and to be beaten <hi>according to his treſpaſſe &amp;c.</hi> And our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> hath taught vs, that he that ſinneth of ignorance muſt be beaten with fewer ſtripes, then he that ſinneth againſt his knowledge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 12.47.48.</note> 
               <hi>That ſeruant</hi> ſaith he <hi>that knew his ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſters will, and prepared not himſelfe, neither did according to his will, ſhall be beaten with many wripes. But he that knew it not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.26</note> 
               <hi>and yet did commit things worthy of ſtripes, ſhall be beaten with few ſtripes.</hi> And this the heathen king e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the light of nature preſcribed vnto <hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—adſit Regula pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quae poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ittoget acquas. Ne ſcutica dignum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li ſectere flagello. Hora. ſerm. l. 1. ſat. 3.</note> that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will not doe the law of God, and the kings law, hee ſhould haue iudgement, <hi>whether it be vnto death, or vnto ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or vnto conffication of goods, or to impriſonment.</hi> Where we ſee, he maketh diuerſities of puniſhments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to he deſert of the offender. <hi>(b)</hi> And vnleſſe this rule be obſerued to proportion puniſhments according to the offences, they ſhall puniſh that with a ſcourge, that ſcarce deſerue a wippe. Fourthly, they muſt conſider the nature and diſpoſition of the partie. Some are more flexible and tender hearted: others are more audacious and deſperate in their wickedneſſe. A leſſer correction will preuaille more with the one, then a greater puniſhment with the other. As <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27.22.</note> 
               <hi>A reproofe entereth more into him that hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then an hundred ſtripes into a foole.</hi> For <hi>though a man ſhould bray a foole in a morter, among wheate, braied with a peſtell, yet will not fooliſhneſſe depart from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt put a difference in puniſhing of theſe. There muſt not bee the like ſeuerity vſed towards them. Where a pinne will ſerue to open an vlcer, there needeth not a launcer. Laſt of all, whatſoeuer the puniſhment be, mercy and compaſſion muſt be vſed in inflicting of it. And therefore the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt not vſe reuiling and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16448:13"/>
ſpeeches, to the diſgrace of the offender. When <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was to proceede againſt <hi>Achan</hi> who by his ſinne had trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.19.</note> hee ſpeaketh to him in milde and gentle tearmes; <hi>My ſonne</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I beſeech thee g ue glory to God, &amp;c.</hi> Neither muſt he by any cruell courſe, make his torture greater or longer, then neceſſitie requireth. For when the delinquent ſhall ſee himſelfe <hi>deſpiſed</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith) in the ſight of him that puniſheth him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25</note> it will bee a meanes to driue him to deſperation. And therefore a godly Father ſaith well, Euen one that iudgeth aright, muſt hold a ballance in his hands, in the one end he muſt beare iuſtice, in the other mercy. By iuſtice he giueth ſentence againſt ſinne,<note n="a" place="margin">Per illam reddit peccati ſententiam, per hanc pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati temperat paenam. Ibid.</note> by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he tempereth and mittigateth the puniſhment of the ſinne. Whereunto agreeth that ſpeech of Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Duo ſunt nomina, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo et pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. quod pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripe, quod ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo miſerere.</note> There are two names, a man and a ſinner: as he is a ſinner puniſh him, as he is a man pittie him. And indeede, mercy is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie eye and light of iuſtice, without which it is nothing but blinde rage and furie.</p>
            <p>But aboue all, mercy muſt be ſhewed to the ſoules of Malefactors. And therefore great care ſhould be had, that by their puniſhments they<note n="c" place="margin">Poenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciem malun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. Tac. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. 1.</note> may be brought to repentance, and not to deſtruction. And this was the end which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt e propounded it puniſhing the <hi>inceſtuous perſon</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by the cenſures of the Church. He comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>he ſhould be deliuered to Satan, for the deſtruction of the fl ſh that the ſpirit might be ſaued in the day of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> The ſword of iuſtice doth continually cut off many wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons for their due deſerts.<note place="margin">1, <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> And as they die a dogges death; ſo it is to be feared, that many of them the like dogges, for want of knowledge and for want of grace. It is a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing, that in ſo great a place as this, there is not ſome godly and ſincere Miniſter appointed to inſtruct them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to prepare them for their ends. I confeſſe this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is famous for many excellent workes of charitie to the bodies of men. The e are many hoſpitals, wherein a great number of poore orphanes and deſolate widowes are libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16448:14"/>
fed and cloathed. No doubt, the <hi>loines of many ſuch that are warmed with your garments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 31.20.</note> 
               <hi>doe bleſſe you, as Iob</hi> ſaith. And many ſicke and wounded perſons by your good prouiſion, doe recouer the health and ſoundneſſe of their bodies. I beſeech you let me begi t at your hands (and who knoweth whether God ſent me hither for this purpoſe or no) that you would adde this worke of mercy to the reſt, which is more excellent then they all, that a competent maintenance may be allowed to ſome faithfull and skilfull Miniſter, who may take care of theſe poore wretches. It were to be wiſhed that there were in euery priſon ſuch a man maintained. For we ſee by experience, that they are nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all vngodlineſſe, and men that once come in priſon, learne more villenie, then euer they knew before. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if there were a godly miniſter to teach and inſtruct them faithfully,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro</hi> 33.12.</note> it were to be hoped, that <hi>in their tribulation they would humble themſelues greatly before the Lord their God,</hi> as we reade <hi>Manaſſes</hi> did, and ſo whatſoeuer became of their bodies, yet their ſoules by Gods mercy might be ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But if this be a worke of too great coſt: yet let me ſo farre preuaile with you in this caſe, that there may be a man of vnderſtanding and knowledge, ſet ouer the ſoules of them that are appointed to die.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 29 13.</note> So ſhall <hi>the bleſſing of thoſe that are readie to periſh,</hi> euen in this life <hi>come vpon you:</hi> and doubtleſſe in the life to come,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>great ſhall be your reward in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the wicked.)</hi> This is the ſecond thing that was noted in the words, namely the equity of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he would not be partiall. It was not likely that when he had done all, he could vtterly purge the land of wicked men. Yet he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo to carrie himſelfe in puniſhing of them, as it ſhould appeare he would doe it without reſpect of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: he would not incline to one more then another. This example doth teach all that is in authority, that in puniſhing malefactors no partiality muſt de vſed. All muſt be puniſhed according to their deſarts, one as well as another. Reſpect of perſons is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16448:14"/>
where condemned in the ſcripture. And firſt in iudging. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was the <hi>Lords</hi> commandement vnto <hi>Magiſtrates, ye ſhall not doe vniuſtly in iudgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.15</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not fauour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the rich, but ſhall Iudge thy neighbour iuſtly.</hi> Giuing vs to vnderſtand, that he that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth partialitie, cannot iudge righteous iudgement.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.19.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Ye ſhall haue no reſpect of perſons in iudgement, but ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great: ye ſhall not feare the face of man; for the iudgement is Gods.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Wreſt not the law, nor reſpect any perſon, &amp;c.</hi> A mighty man muſt not be feared for his greatneſſe, nor a meane man muſt not be deſpiſed for his pouerty. And <hi>Dauid</hi> in the perſon of the <hi>Lord</hi> reprouing the corrupt &amp; wicked magiſtrates of his time ſaith, <hi>How long will ye iudge vniuſtly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.2.</note> 
               <hi>and accept the perſon of the wicked?</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> in diuerſe places doth the like. <hi>It is not good,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to accept the perſon of the wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>to cauſe the righteous to fal in iudgement.</hi> And <hi>It is not good to haue reſpect of any perſon in iudgement.</hi> And againe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.23.</note> 
               <hi>To haue reſpect of perſons is not good: for that man will tranſgreſſe for a piece of bread.</hi> Hereupon the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> chargeth <hi>Timotheus</hi> euen <hi>before God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels,</hi> that in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the eccleſiaſticall cenſures vpon wicked perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21</note> he ſhould <hi>not preferre one before another,</hi> and that he ſhould <hi>doe nothing partially.</hi> Wher he vſeth two words of great ſignification.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The firſt doth ſignifie to eſteeme highly of ſome one man in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of others, which is moſt intollerable in a Iudge, who muſt ſit in the place of iuſtice, not to iudge of mens perſons, but according to their cauſes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Beza.</note> The ſecond is borrowed from him that holdeth the ballance, implying that the Iudge muſt waigh the cauſes of men that are at variance, as it were in a balance, ſo as he muſt incline to neither part, otherwiſe there can be no right iudgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this reſpect of perſons, and this parcialitie is condemned alſo in puniſhing. When the <hi>Lord</hi> had appointed puniſhments by way of <hi>retaliation,</hi> vnto him that had any way hurt his brother, hee addeth in the end.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16448:15"/>
               <hi>Ye ſhall haue one law, it ſhall be as well for the ſtranger, as for one borne in the country.</hi> The ſtranger if he deſerue fauour, muſt haue as much ſauour, as if he were borne in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and he that is borne in the country, muſt be puniſhed with as much ſeuerity, as if he were a ſtranger. Againe, the <hi>Lord</hi> commandeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 17.25</note> 
               <hi>If there be found among you in any of thy cities, which the Lord thy God giu th thee, man or woman that hath wrought wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dneſſe in the ſight of the Lord thy God &amp;c. then thou ſhalt bring foorth that man or that woman vnto thy gates, and ſhalt ſtone them with ſtones till thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> We ſee here is none excepted. Whoſoeuer they be that tranſgreſſe, high or low, rich or poore, they muſt be puniſhed. And therefore in ſome caſes, it were not lawfull for the father or mother to ſpare their owne ſonne, that was borne of their bone, and fleſh of their fleſh. <hi>If any man haue a ſonne</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that is ſtubburne and diſobedient,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>which will not hearken to the voice of his father, nor the vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of his mother &amp;c. then ſhall his father and his mother take him and bring him out vnto t e El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his citie, and then all the men of his citie ſhall ſtone him with ſtones vnto death.</hi> Yea there is not any bond of nature or of friendſhip, that ſhould hinder a man from the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duetie, according to that ſtrict charge and precept of the Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6.7.8.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>If thy brother the ſonne of thy mother, or thine owne ſonne, or thy daughter, or thy wife that lieth in thy boſome, or thy friend which is as thine owne ſoule, entice thee ſecretly,</hi> ſaying, <hi>let vs goe and ſerue us other Gods, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not conſent vnto him nor h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are him neither ſhall thine eie pitie him, nor ſhew mercy nor keepe him ſecret. But thou ſhalt eu n kill him: thine hand ſhall be firſt vpon him to put him to death and then the hands of all the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Aſa,</hi> king of <hi>Iudah</hi> is commended in the word of God, for his vprightneſſe in this reſpect, that when <hi>Maacha</hi> his owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther committed idolatry, he would not ſpare her but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed her, euen <hi>by depoſing her from her regency</hi> And indeede, it is truely ſaid,<note n="a" place="margin">Iuſtitium non nouit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit matte n, ventatem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> knoweth neither father nor mother, but onely the truth. As <hi>Moſes</hi> teſtifieth of <hi>Leui,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16448:15"/>
that he ſaid vnto his father and to his mothe, I haue not ſeene him, neither knew he his brethren, nor knew his owne children:</hi> ſo muſt it be with euery good <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> The neereſt kinſmen and deareſt friends that he hath in the world muſt haue no more fauour then other men. Beſides, the Lord hath entitled and ſtiled <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> by the name of <hi>Gods,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ſtandeth in the aſſembly of gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1.6</note> 
               <hi>he iudgeth among Gods.</hi> And againe, <hi>I haue ſaid ye are gods, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore, as they communicate with God in his name, ſo alſo they ſhould follow his example. Now the Scripture doth euery where teach vs, that God is no reſpecter of perſons. <hi>The Lord your God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, is God of gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17 18.</note> 
               <hi>and Lord of Lords, a great God, mighty and terrible, which excepteth no perſons, nor taketh reward, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> exhorting his Iudges that he had made, to the due execution of iuſtice, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Gods example as an argument to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <hi>Let the feare of the Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be vpon you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 19.7</note> 
               <hi>take heed and doe it, for there is no iniquity with the Lrrd our God, neither reſpect of perſons nor receiuing of reward.</hi> And <hi>Elihu</hi> affirmeth the ſame in the booke of <hi>Iob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 34.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord accepteth not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, and regardeth not the rich more then the poore: for they be all the worke of his hands.</hi> The greateſt and the richeſt are like to finde no more fauour at his hands then the meaneſt and the pooreſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3.</note> for he made the one as well as the other. And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of the kingdome and dominion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaith, <hi>He ſhall not iudge after the ſight of his eyes,</hi> he ſhall not bee caried with outward reſpects to condemne or abſolue any man without cauſe. In a word, the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> that <hi>God without reſpect of perſons iudgeth according to euery mans worke.</hi> And we ſee by experience, that the greateſt <hi>potentates,</hi> and mightieſt <hi>monarches</hi> in the world, can no more eſcape the vengeance of God, then the pooreſt wretches that liue vpon the earth. Witneſſe <hi>Pharaoh, Nabuchad-nezzar</hi> and diuerſe others, whom God brought to confuſion notwithſtanding all their pride. Neither can the greateſt multitude of ſinners that are, reſcue themſelues
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16448:16"/>
from the ſtroake of his puniſhing hand, no more then if they were but a few, or but one perſon, as we ſee in the <hi>old world,</hi> in <hi>Sodome and Gomorha,</hi> and the cities about them, and in the great army of <hi>Sennacherib.</hi> Yea the Lord correcteth his deareſt children, euen as well as thoſe that are his enemies. As the <hi>Apoſtle Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 17.</note> ſaith, <hi>The time is come that iudgement muſt beginne at the houſe of God.</hi> And the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe ſaith to the wicked nations <hi>Loe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>I beginne to plague the citie where my name is called vpon, and ſhould you goe free?</hi> And ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the children and poſteritie of <hi>Dauid</hi> whom he loued ſo dearely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30.31.32.33.</note> as he promiſed that he would <hi>Neuer take his lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſſe from them:</hi> ſaith notwithſtanding, that <hi>If they forſake his law, and walke not in his iudgements: if they breake his ſtatutes, and keepe not his commandements; he would viſit their tranſgreſſion with the rod, and their iniquitie with ſtrokes.</hi> Thus ſhould it be with al <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet</hi> 2.9.</note> They ſhould labour to expreſſe this excellet vertue of him that hath called them out of darkeneſſe into his maruelous light. They muſt ſuffer nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great nor ſmall, one nor other to eſcape deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.<note n="a" place="margin">Cauendum eſt ne uſdem de cauſis alij plectantur, In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e appell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntur qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic. of c. li. 1.</note> They muſt take heede that for one and the ſame fault, ſome be not puniſhed, and others not once cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in queſtion.<note n="b" place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de Con. ſid. ib. 2.</note> The magiſtrate (as <hi>Bernard</hi> told <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>) maketh himſelfe guilty of no ſmall offence, if he doe reſpect the countenances of ſinners, and doe not rather iudge according to the merit of their cauſes. As it is ſaid of the law, that it can neither be moued witſt fauour, nor weakned with power, nor corrupted with money: ſo it ſhould be with the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Nihil offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, nihil gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e dabitur. Sen.</note> Neither feare nor fauour ſhould diuert him from that which is right. As the <hi>Sinne</hi> is no other to a a rich man, then to a poore man, but indifferent to all, parching, or refreſhing all alike: So muſt the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry himſelfe equally and indifferently to all men in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice. The rich muſt not be more fauoured then the poore, nor the poore more ſeuerely dealt withall then the rich. It is reported by trauellers, that in <hi>Zante</hi> ouer the place of iudgement, where all cauſes both criminall &amp; iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all are decided, there are two <hi>Latine</hi> verſes written in letters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16448:16"/>
of gold, on the wall, to this effect.<note n="d" place="margin">Hic locus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, amat, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, conſeruat honorat. Nequitiam, pacean, crumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, iura, bono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This place hateth wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes, loueth peace, puniſheth offences, preſerueth the laws, honoureth the good. Implying that there ſhall be no partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie vſed, but euery man ſhall be proceeded withall according to his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s be they good or euill. At <hi>Athens</hi> the iudges cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Areopagit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did ſit in iudgement vpon cauſes in the night time, that no outward and occaſion or reſpect might worke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their affections to moue them either to ſeuerity or to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the equity of the thing required.<note n="e" place="margin">Cael. Rhodi. lib. 10. cap. 3.</note> And in <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> the image of <hi>Iupiter</hi> was made without cares: inſinuating that a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ſhould heare no mans complaint nor peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely follow that, which the ballance of reaſon, and the ſincerity of vncorrupted iuſtice did ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>Here then are all ſuch iuſtly reproued, as are careleſſe and negligent in this reſpect As we ſee by common experience, that many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hes in place of iuſtice, there is now much partiality If they be great perſons and rich men that offend, they are ſeldome puniſhed. I pray God it may not be true at this day, which the heathen <hi>Oratour</hi> obſerued of his times.<note n="f" place="margin">Omnium ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mone percre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu, his iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis quae nunc ſunt, pecunio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum hominem quamuis ſit no cena, neminem poſſe damnari. Cic. in Ver. protem. 1. act.</note> It is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon in euery mans mouth, that in theſe iudgements which are now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o money man though he be an offender, can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.<note n="g" place="margin">Nihil tam ſanctum, quod non viola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil tam muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod non expugnari pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia poteſt. ibid.</note> And indeed there is nothing ſo pure &amp; holy that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be violated, nothing ſo well fenſed that cannot be won &amp; ouercome with money. But the laws muſt nor be like vnto cobwebs, which catch and hold the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> flies, but the great ones break through them. Others there be that ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be turned out of the way by hundred &amp; acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and friendſhip and ſuch like reſpects. Wherby it commeth to paſſe, that according to the old prouerbe, <hi>ſome man may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſteale an horſe, then another may looke on.</hi> If he be <hi>Couſin to we,</hi> as the ſaying is, if he be well allied, let his fact be what it wil be he need not ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, he ſhall neuer be called into queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or if he be, hee ſhall quickly be diſcharged. But <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> ought to know that there is no nerenes of kindred or allia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that ſhold be any patronage for ſin. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord was wroth with the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for making the golden calfe. <hi>Moſes</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the ſons of <hi>Leui,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.27.</note> 
               <hi>to put euery man his ſword by his ſide
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16448:17"/>
and to goe to and fro from gate to gate through the hoſt, and ſlay euery man his brother, and euery man his companion, and euery man his neighbour.</hi> They muſt ſpare none, how neare or deare ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Hae rog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes miſtam ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsitatem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent Cacl. Calcag. de rat. iudicandi.</note>There are many alſo, that for feare of greater perſons, are kept from executing iuſtice. For as hath beene ſaid before, Mightie men will become ſuiters to inferiour Magiſtrates in the behalfe of offenders whom they affect. And as one ſaith well, <hi>(a)</hi> their requeſt bringeth a neceſſity with them. For vnleſſe their deſire be ſatisfied, and the party whom they commend be abſolued, by right or wrong, be his cauſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo bad, they will be ſure to ſit on their skirts, and one time or other they will come euen with them. As we reade of <hi>Agiſclaus,</hi> who when he commended a friend of his to the Iudge, he requeſted him, that if his cauſe were good, hee would abſoule him for iuſtice ſake, if not that he would ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his deſire: but howſoeuer the world went that he would abſolue him. By this meanes it commeth to paſſe, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notorious lewd perſons, are ſubduced from deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and reſerued to commit greater villenies, to the diſhonour of God, and the hurt of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>And therefore all magiſtrates are to be exhorted, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for equall and vpright dealing in puniſhing offences. They ſhould ſhew themſelues ſo inuincible and ſo impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable againſt all affections, as neither by force of money, nor by the feare or fauour of any man whoſoeuer, they ſuffer themſelues to be drawne away from the right. <hi>Courage</hi> is the principall vertue, and the chiefe badge of a <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21</note> When <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thro</hi> perſwaded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make and appoint rulers vnder himſelfe, <hi>euer thouſands, euer hundreds, euer fifties, and ouer tens.</hi> The firſt thing that he required in them was this, that the ſhould be <hi>Men of courage.</hi> And when <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was appointed to ſucceede <hi>Moſes</hi> in the gouernment of the people of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Moſes called him and ſaid vnto him in the ſight of all the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> 
               <hi>Be of a good courage and ſtrong.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16448:17"/>
And after that the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue him the ſame charge twice for fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good courage</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would expell &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riue away a I cowardly an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fainthe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23 <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.1.</note> &amp; cauſe them manually and ſtrongly to execute iuſtice, though there be neuer ſo many impediments to encounter with al. And herein the very h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athen men may be our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lemaiſters For if <hi>Solomon</hi> ſend the <hi>Slugg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd to the piſmire to learne</hi> inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why ſhold we ſcorne to earne of paga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s who were endued with excellent gifts of nature.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> a great <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> when his ſon in law <hi>Charillus</hi> was to be endited for extortion, would not ſo much as be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there leaſt his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce might haue procured him ſome fauor, aſſuming that when he tooke him to be his ſon in law, he hoped he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a good &amp; an honeſt man.<note n="a" place="margin">Plutarch in praecept polit</note> And <hi>Cleon</hi> when hee was called to be a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſent preſently for all his friends, and renounced then f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>dſhip. And when <hi>Simonides</hi> requeſted ſomething of <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtocles,</hi> a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> that was not very iuſt, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m with this anſwer. He is not a good <hi>Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out harmony, nor he a good mag ſtrate that ſheweth any fauour a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt the lawes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut there is a moſt famous exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all other for this purpoſe recorded by <hi>Aelianus.</hi> The ſum of it is this. There was a man of the people called <hi>Mardi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A han. lib. 1. cap 34.</note> that had ſeauen ſonnes, whereof the youngeſt being ſtubborne and diſſolute and one that would not be reclaimed the rather taketh him, and bindes his hands behind him, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought him to the Iudges: &amp; there doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arneſtly accuſe him, &amp; required that he might bee put to death. The Iudges being aſtoniſhed at the ſtrangenes of the thing would not meddle with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, but brought the father and the ſon to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King. Where the father ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed againſt the ſon &amp; craued iuſtice. The King ſeeing his ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtneſſe, ſaid vnto him. Canſt thou then with thine owne e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e endure to behold the death of thy ſon? he anſw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, yea very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el For when I ſhall ſee him, that wrongeth &amp; diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth my family, put to death, Land the reſt of my children ſhall liue with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eater comfort When the King heard this he highly commended the father, &amp; made him one of his Iudges, affirming, that he that durſt ſo ſeuerely &amp; ſo iuſtly pronounce ſentence againſt his owne childe, would doubtleſſe ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16448:18"/>
a ſincere &amp; incorrupt iudge vnto others. But he pardoned the young man for that time, threatning to put him to a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible death if euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould offend againe in the l ke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h that our Magiſtrates and Iudges would follow th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe examples. For if it did once appeare to the world that rich &amp; mighty men ſhould be puniſhed as well as the poore &amp; meane perſons and that kinsfolke &amp; friends ſhould finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o more fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur then thoſe that are ſtrangers, it would ſoone cut off all hope of impu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e from all kinde of malefactors. And bleſſed be God, that at this time our eies do ſee the great care of his Maieſty to haue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloud, wherwith it hath been poluted, &amp; that there is ſo ſtrict &amp; ſo iuſt proceeding againſt all that were co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in ſo wicked a fact. nd the Lord ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hart &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that moſt wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Lord chiefe Iuſtice that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſtil go forward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to cut off al thoſe that had any a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſo foul a murder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wicked.)</hi> As all the wicked muſt be puniſhed without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie ſo none but the wicked muſt be enda gered. Th y that are innocent and harme eſſe, muſt not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſted. The Lord, commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> that in the execution o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1 <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.15</note> 
               <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhould bee iuſtified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the wicked condemned</hi> And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is as great abhomination in the ſight of od to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the iuſt, as it is to iuſtifie the wicke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And the <hi>Prophet</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth as great a <hi>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im that <hi>Taketh away the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſ es of the r ghteous from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.23.</note> as againſt him <hi>That iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th &amp; abſolueth the wick d for a reward</hi> The Lord hath pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſword into the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 4</note> but it is to this e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, that he may <hi>Take vengean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him that doth euill.</hi> And therefore bee abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and abuſeth his ſword, if he turneth edge of it againſt the godly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 11 2.</note> and ſmite them that <hi>are vpright in heart,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith. This is a moſt fearefull and a moſt horrible ſinne and a ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne which God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt ſeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rely puniſh. Among thoſe <hi>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en things</hi> which the <hi>Lord hateth</hi> and abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 6.16 17 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this is one, <hi>The hands that ſhed innocent blood</hi> And <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auid</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>make inquiſition for blood.</hi> Sometimes inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſhed vnder colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw But there will be at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, when the Lord wil c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e with a queſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to find it out, nd to puniſh it. And therefore, when the wicked brought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16448:18"/>
the <hi>Prophet Ieremiah</hi> before the princes, and would haue had him put to death, he ſpeaketh to them with great boldneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 26.14.15</note> 
               <hi>As for me, I am in your hands, doe with me as you thinke good, But know ye for a certaine, that if you put me to death, ye ſhall ſurely bring innocent blood vpon your ſelues, and vpon this city, &amp; vpon the inhabitants therof.</hi> Implying, that God would reuenge his blood, not onely vpon the murderers themſelues, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people, the whole land ſhould be guilty of it. When poore <hi>Naboth</hi> was vniuſtly condemned and put to death by wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent <hi>Elijah</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> to him with this meſſag. <hi>Haſt thou killed &amp; alſo gotten poſſeſsion? Thus ſaith the Lord in the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth ſhal dogs licke euen thy blood alſo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.13.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.38. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 21.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.2.3.4</note> Which came to paſſe accordingly <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was a cruell murderer, <hi>He ſhed innocent blood excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much, till he repleniſhed Ieruſalem from corner to corner.</hi> But marke how fearefully the <hi>Lord</hi> reuenged this ſin in his poſterity. In the daies of <hi>Iehoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kim. The Lord ſent againſt him bands of the Caldees, &amp; bands of the Aramits, &amp; bands of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abites, &amp; bands of the Amonites &amp; he ſent them againſt Iudah, to deſtroy it. Surly by the commandment of the Lord came this vpon Iudah, that he might put them out of ſight, for the ſinnes of Manaſſeh, And for the innocent blood that he ſhed, therefore the Lord would not pardon it. Manaſſeh</hi> was dead &amp; rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time but we ſee the Lord had not forgotten his ſin, but the whole land ſmarted for it in the third generation after him. So likewiſe <hi>Ioaſh</hi> moſt vnkindly cauſed <hi>Zechariah</hi> the ſon of good <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oiada</hi> to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtoned to death, becauſe he reproued him for his idolatry. But ſee what followed.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 24.21.22.23.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>When the yeare was out the hoſt of Aram came vp againſt him, and they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iudah and Ieruſalem and deſtroyed all the Princes of the people from among the people and ſent all the ſpoile of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King of Damaſcus. Though the army of Aram came with a ſmall company of men, yet the Lord deliuered a very great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, the Lord ſomte him with <hi>great diſſeaſes.</hi> And at the laſt, <hi>his owne ſeruants conſpired againſt him,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16448:19"/>
and ſlew him on his bed.</hi> And the reaſon of all theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is giuen there by the holy Ghoſt, that they were <hi>For the blood of the children of Iehoiada the Prieſt.</hi> And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lord did threaten the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35</note> that <hi>Vpon them ſhould come all the righteous blood that was ſhed vpon the earth, from the blood of Abel the righteous, vnto the blood of Zacharias the ſonne of Barachias, whom they ſlew betweene the temple and the altar.</hi> When the wicked <hi>Iewes</hi> were ſo earneſt with <hi>Pilate</hi> to haue our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> put to death, and he would haue teſtified his innocencie in the matter, they all with one voice took it vpon themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.25</note> and cried out, <hi>His blood be on vs, and on our children.</hi> Which fearfull imprecation of theirs the Lord did heare, and auenged his blood vpon them with a witnes. Neither was there any ſinne ſo ſeuerely puniſhed as that ſinne. For the <hi>Lord</hi> brought an vtter deſtruction vpon the whole nation, that euen to this day they are deſperſed and ſcattered throughout the whole earth, and may euen be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the common Rogues and vagabonds of the world. And <hi>Pilate</hi> that wicked iudge, that pronounced that wicked ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt him, to gratifie and pleaſe the <hi>Iewes,</hi> euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his conſcience,<note place="margin">Euſeb li. 2 c. 7.</note> did not eſcape the reuenging hand of God. For the Lord brought vpon him ſuch wofull calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that to be rid out of his paine, he thruſt himſelfe through with his owne hands, and ſo ended his wretched life. In a word, we reade in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> that <hi>the ſoules of them that were killed for the word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>and for the teſtimony which they maintained, doe crie with a loud voice vnder the altar: How long Lord, holy and true! doſt thou not iudge and auenge our bloode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them that dwell vpon the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all this that hath beene ſpoken, we ſee what a fearefull ſinne it is to be guilty of ſhedding innocent blood. And yet we ſee it by too much experience, that where wicked men are in authority, they that are moſt godly, and moſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, are ſure to be moſt moleſted. Is it not an ordinary thing with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> where they haue the law in their hands, to puniſh a man more ſeuerely, for reading the holy word of
<pb facs="tcp:16448:19"/>
God, for the comfort and education of his ſoule, at for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fleſh on a friday, or for breaking any of their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ceremonies, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either for blaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>my, or drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or whordome, of for mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er it ſelfe? For though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man bee guilty of theſe ſinnes, hee may haue a diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a pardon: but if he bee taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardie in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the other, hee is ſure to bee burnt at a ſtake, and to fry a fagot. And others alſo that are no <hi>Papiſts,</hi> at leaſt would be counted none, as farre as their power will ſtretch, doe moſt of all manifeſt their malice againſt the children of God. I know they are aſhamed openly to profeſſe this. But they haue other ſhifts and other pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſes for their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. If <hi>Haman</hi> deſire to haue the whole nation of the <hi>Iewes</hi> deſtroyed, there ſhall not bee the leaſt inſinuation, that it is becauſe they are the people of God: that were too groſſe. But <hi>They doe not obſerue the Kings Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 3.8.</note> and therefore, <hi>It is not th Kings profit to ſuffer them.</hi> If the <hi>Iewes</hi> conſpire the <hi>Prophet Ieremiahs</hi> death, the quarell muſt not be, becauſe he is a faithfull <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> and will bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeake all that the Lord commandeth him to ſpeake: that were too ſhamefull. But forſooth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 26.11.</note> 
               <hi>He propheſieth againſt the citie,</hi> and therefore <hi>he is worthy to die.</hi> If flattering <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiah</hi> the <hi>Prieſt of Bethel</hi> would bring poore <hi>Amos</hi> into diſgrace with <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> the pretence and colour of his ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſation muſt be this.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>Amos hath conſpired againſt thee in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ands of the houſe of Iſrael: the land is not able to beare all his words.</hi> When the <hi>Iewes</hi> were purpoſed to cruſifie our bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour the Lord of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.46.</note> though they could find nothing in him that was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (for there was none of them that could true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>rebuke him of ſinne</hi>) yet this they falſely pretended againſt him. <hi>That they found him peruerting the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to pay tribute to Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſar,</hi> and that <hi>he ſpake againſt Caeſar in making himſelfe a King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.12 <hi>Act.</hi> 6.10.</note> When the aduerſaries of <hi>Saint Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> ſought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>de the maine quarell was becauſe <hi>they were not able to reſiſt the wiſedome and the ſpirit by which he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake.</hi> But yet they had another manner of accuſation againſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16448:20"/>
him, namely, <hi>that he ceaſed not to ſpeake blaſphemous words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy place, and againſt the law.</hi> In like manner when <hi>Ananias the high Prieſt and the elders</hi> went about to put the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> to death, they had as farre a cloake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or their vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leinous intent as could be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24 1.2 5.</note> They hired a skilfull lawyer to accuſe him, <hi>to be a p ſtilent fellow and a mouer of ſedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Iewes throughout the world.</hi> And doubtleſſe, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vngodly men at this day, are not leſſe ingenious, nor leſſe malicious, to deuiſe falſe accuſations agai ſt thoſe that are moſt ſincere, and ſo farre as is in their power, to bring them within compaſſe of law, when as in truth if they would ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riue themſelues, their owne heart telleth them, that their quarell againſt them, is no other, then <hi>Cains</hi> was againſt his brother <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.12.</note> euen <hi>becauſe their owne workes are euill and the others good.</hi> And therefore, let all thoſe whom this may concerne be admoniſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.24</note> to <hi>waſh their hands</hi> but with a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer conſcience and a cleaner heart then <hi>Pilate</hi> did) from the innocent blood of all iuſt perſons. Let them take heede, that they haue no hand, vpon any pretence whatſoeuer, not onely in the dead, but not in the vniuſt moleſtation, or wrongfull puniſhment of any that are knowne to bee godly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Betimes.)</hi> or early. This noteth his ſpeede and diligence in puniſhing offenders he promiſeth to doe it ſpeedily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, diligently without remiſneſſe, and conſtantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion. From whence we may obſerue, that they that are to puniſh others, muſt doe it ſpeedily. This was the commiſsion that was giuen to <hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.26.</note> that <hi>Whoſoeuer would doe the the law of his God &amp; the Kings law, he muſt haue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without delay.</hi> That which God commandeth to houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders and fathers of families: namely, that if they loue their children they muſt <hi>Correct them betimes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 13.14 <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.18.</note> and <hi>chaſten them whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is hope:</hi> is alſo required of <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and fathers of the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ry: that in puniſhing of ſinne they muſt begin early and betimes, leaſt it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſlacke, and remiſſe, they doe not in time conuenient, and in due ſeaſon,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16448:20"/>
meete with thoſe euils that are to bee reformed. So that if <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> take heede, that they giue not way to raſh and vnaduiſed anger, and that they bee tranſported and caried headlong with inconſiderate paſsion, they cannot beginne ſoone enough to puniſh thoſe that doe offend. For as in all other caſes, ſo in this eſpecially delay hath dangers. For by this meanes ſin gathereth ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th As fire that is not preſently quenched, cauſeth great ruine. So iniquity that is not quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſed, breedeth great miſchiefe in the common-wealth.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>Vide ego quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erat primo ſanabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vulnus, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gae d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mna tu iſſe morae.</p>
                  <p>Principiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur, Cum mala per longas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere moras. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. de rem d. amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is l b. 1. Et neglecta ſolent in cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſumere vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat. l. 1. Epiſt. 18. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.27 <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.9.10.</p>
               </note> As a wound or a diſeaſe that is not taken in time, prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many times inueterate and incurable: ſo euill that is not preuented in the beginning, ſpreadeth often to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſtate. If <hi>Ioab</hi> had receiued puniſhment according to his deſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, at the firſt for killing <hi>Abner,</hi> he would not haue growne ſo audaciouſly inſolent, as he did afterwards, to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Amaſa</hi> ſo treacherouſly. Againe, it is to be obſerued, that the Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et <hi>Dauid</hi> doth here vſe the plurall number. For in the or ginall it is <hi>in the mornings.</hi> Whereby he noteth his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtoutneſſe in performing of this dutie. Becauſe it were not ſufficient for a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> once or twice ſeuerely to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſh wicked men, vnleſſe he doe conſtantly perſeuere in the ſame And therefore in a word, not to inſiſt any longer on this point, here is condemned the careleſneſſe and remiſnes of many <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> who though they ſee lewd and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons, to ruſh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with impudent and ſhameleſſe boldneſſe: yet either for feare, or for fauour, doe protract the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from day to day and dare not or will not puniſh them. Let them remember that God himſelfe hath armed them with a ſword,<note n="b" place="margin">In matutinis Calum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n loc. ſingulis matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s. Tremel.</note> that they ſhould not onely ſtoutly and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but alſo quickly and ſpeed ly execute his iudgements. And let them know, that if they faile herein in any reſpect whatſoeuer, they are lyabl to that curſe denounced by the <hi>Prophet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10</note> 
               <hi>Curſ d he he that doth th worke of the Lord negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and curſed b h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od giueth him a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to kill, <hi>keepeth backe his ſword from blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Workers of iniquity)</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Prophet</hi> expoundeth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16448:21"/>
what he meant by thoſe whom he called <hi>wicked</hi> in the former part of the verſe. Which teacheth vs that all workers of iniquity are wicked men. I know men thinke ſcorne of this and they wil by no meanes endure to heare of it. And indeed it is an odious name, &amp; all that are ſuch are in a fearful eſtate. But ſti l in the iudgement of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> they are all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wicked and vngodly perſons that doe <hi>worke iniquitie.</hi> Our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> affirmeth it with as great earneſtneſſe as may be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> 
               <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, that whoſoeuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne is the ſeruant of ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 3.8.</note> And his <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh the matter yet worſe. <hi>He that committeth ſinne is of the diuell.</hi> But here peraduenture it will be obiected,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 2 B. 9.</note> that all are ſinners, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>who can ſay, I haue made my heart cleane, I am cleane from my ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kin</hi> 8.46 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8</note> And in another place, <hi>there is no man that ſinneth not.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> confeſſeth, that <hi>if we ſay we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and there is no truth in vs.</hi> And ſo by this reckoning all ſhould be <hi>wicked</hi> men. I anſwer, that it is true indeede, all men are ſinners: but yet there is great difference of ſinners. Some are penitent, and ſome are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners. But to the end, that wee may conceiue this point aright, we will diſtinguiſh of ſinners foure ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall waies. Firſt, in reſpect of the meaſure. Secondly, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the manner of their ſinning. Thirdly, in reſpect of their continuance in ſinne. Fourthly, in reſpect of the vſe that they make of their ſinnes. For the firſt. There is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the Godly and the wicked in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Iud. ve. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> The godly, though they haue in them the ſeedes of all ſinne, yet they doe not commit all ſinne:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9.</note> but by the mercy of God they are kept from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into many ſinnes. The ſeede of grace and regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in them, and that preſerueth them, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſinne as the wicked doe. And therefore, the childe of God may ſpeake that ſincerely, which the arrogant <hi>Phariſe</hi> ſpake proudly and vainely:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11.</note> 
               <hi>O God I thanke thee, that I am not as other men.</hi> I am not giuen to <hi>extortion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16448:21"/>
to iniuſtice, to adultery</hi> and ſuch like ſinnes, as other men are. But the wicked commit all kinde of ſinne whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, if either ſhame of the world, or feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe not reſtraine them. Their life, is a life of ſinne. As the <hi>Prophet Ieremiah</hi> inſinuateth, when he biddeth the people, <hi>Amend their waies and their workes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 7 3.</note> All their waies are ſinfull waies, and all their workes are wicked workes, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaking of the wickedneſſe of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>They were full of all vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and then reckoneth vp a long beadrow of vices wherein they liued. And in another place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.29.30 <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.19</note> 
               <hi>They gaue themſelues vnto wantonneſſe, to worke all vncleaneneſſe.</hi> They make no bones of any ſinne whatſoeuer it be: there is nothing too hot or too heauy for them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is difference betweene them in the manner of their ſinning. For firſt, the godly ſinne, but it is ſore againſt their wils.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23</note> As the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: that <hi>The law of his members</hi> (that is, his corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>rebelled againſt the law of his minde, and leade him captive vnto the law of ſinne.</hi> The Apoſtle ſinned then, but it was neither with heart nor good will, as wee ſay: but hee was hailed and drawne to it forcibly, by the ſtrength of his corruption, and the violence of his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, euen as a priſoner is hailed to the gaile. But the wicked, they ſinne willingly, voluntarily, and of their owne accord, <hi>They fulfill the will of the fleſh and of the minde,</hi> as <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith. Againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> the godly doe but ſeldome fall into ſinne in compariſon of the wicked. They are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ouertaken with it, but ſtill the whole courſe of their life is bent to doe that which God commandeth. As a ſeruant may ſometimes doe a chare for another man, and yet chiefely and principally minde his maiſters buſineſſe. And therefore, it is ſaid of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that hee <hi>Did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>and turned from nothing that hee commanded him, all the daies of his life, ſaue onely in the matter of Vrijah the Hittite.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16448:22"/>
But the wicked ſinne continually, they doe nothing but ſinne it is their daily practiſe they make it their ordinary trade and occupation.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 21.25.</note> As it is ſaid of <hi>Ahab,</hi> that <hi>he did ſell himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the fight of the Lord.</hi> Moreouer, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne, but it is with griefe and ſorrow of heart, they take no more pleaſure nor delight in their ſinne, then the horſe doth in his heauy loade, or the priſoners in his irons and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> crieth out as if he were ouer tyred with the maſſe of ſinne that was in his fleſh.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.16.</note> But the wicked ſinne with delight and ioy, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>They reioice in doing euill.</hi> Nay they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>they cannot ſleepe quietly in their beds except they haue done euill.</hi> Laſt of all, the godly ſinne with reſiſtance. They wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and ſtriue againſt their ſinnes by praier, by faſting and all other good meanes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit,</hi> that is the generate part, continually <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſteth</hi> and fighteth <hi>againſt the fleſh.</hi> And this the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſheweth by his owne experience.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.19.</note> 
               <hi>I allow not</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that which I doe. And, I doe not the good that I would: but the euill which I would not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">25.</note> 
               <hi>that I doe.</hi> And againe, <hi>I my ſelfe in my minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erue the law of God but in my fleſh the law of ſinne.</hi> The godly then are in a continuall combate and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>flict againſt their ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4.</note> But the wicked are caried headlong to ſinne with full ſway, with their whole endeauour and with all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcements that may be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.6.</note> They turne to their ſinfull courſes, with as great violence as <hi>the horſe ruſheth into the battell. They worke all vncleaneneſſe euen with greedineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.19</note> Neither did the hungry fiſh more eagerly and greedily follow after the baite, then they doe purſue and hunt after the occaſions of ſinne. Yea, they ſtriue euery one to excell other. <hi>Their feete runne to euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa</hi> 59.7. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 4</note> 
               <hi>and they make haſt to ſhed innocent blood.</hi> And they <hi>runne into all exceſſe of riot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly there is difference in their continuance in ſinne. The godly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 24.16</note> though <hi>They fall ſeauen times a day,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith: yet <hi>they riſe againe,</hi> they renew their acqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tance, as oft as they renue their ſinnes. That which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16448:22"/>
of <hi>anger</hi> in particular, that a godly man will not ſuffer <hi>the ſunne to goe downe vpon his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.26.</note> that they practiſe in all ſinne. They will not ſleepe in any ſinne; but continually <hi>breake of their ſinnes by righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.24.</note> as <hi>Daniel</hi> exhorted that proud King of <hi>Babylon.</hi> But the wicked dwell and continue in their ſinnes: they he along, yea they wallow, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umble and welt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r themſelues in them, as the ſow doth in the mire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thought of riſing againe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Rom</hi> 2.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.18 <hi>&amp;.</hi> 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>They ſit downe in the ſeate of the ſcornfull.</hi> They haue brought ſuch <hi>an hardneſſe</hi> vpon their hearts, by the cuſtome and continuall vſe of ſinning, as that <hi>they cannot repent.</hi> They are ſo farre from breaking of the courſe of their ſinnes, as <hi>they draw iniquity with cordes of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ſinne, as it were, with cartropes</hi> Yea <hi>they lay</hi> or heape <hi>ſinne vpon ſinne,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19</note> 
               <hi>adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt.</hi> And being by the iuſt iudgement of God giuen ouer and left to themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.27</note> 
               <hi>they fall from one wickedneſſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, they differ in the vſe they make of their ſinnes. The godly are made more wary and more heedfull for the time to come, and more carefull to auoid all occaſions of ſinne. And this the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> affirmeth, when ſpeaking of the fruites of true repentance and godly ſorrow, he ſaith, that it wrought in them <hi>great care, great indignation great feare, great deſire, &amp;c.</hi> We ſay in our common prouerbe.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10 11.</note> 
               <hi>The burnt childe dreadeth the fire.</hi> So a man that hath beene burnt in the hand by his ſinne, that hath felt the diſpleaſure of God, and the horrour of conſcience by reaſon thereof, will take heede how he falleth any more into ſinne while he liueth. But the wicked, the more they ſinne, the more bold and audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they are to ſinne againe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.12.</note> They haue gotten <hi>an wheres forehead, they cannot bluſh. Were they aſhamed when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey had committed ſu h abhominations;</hi> ſaith the <hi>Prophet Ieremiah, nay, they were not aſhamed, neither could they haue any ſhame,</hi> they were paſt ſhame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>The triall of their countenance doth teſtifie againſt them, yea they declare their ſinnes as Sodome, they hide them not.</hi> They care not who ſeeth them. To this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16448:23"/>
purpoſe <hi>Bernard</hi> hath a very excellent ſaying.<note place="margin">Bern. in. Pſ l. 91. ſerm. 2. Ho. intereſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er pio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um et implorum c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c.</note> There is this difference, ſaith he, betweene the fals of the godly and the wicked: that a righteous man is vpholden by the <hi>Lord</hi> and therefore, he riſeth againe ſtronger then euer he was: but when an vnrighteous man falleth, he neuer riſeth againe. Nay he is ſo farre from riſing, that either hee falleth into hurtfull ſhame, or elſe into flat impudency For either he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth that which he doth, and that is a ſhame that maketh a man ſinne more; or elſe he hath an whores forehead, ſo as he neither feareth God, nor careth for man. A righteous man hee falleth vpon Gods hand, and after a maruellous manner, euen his ſinne is turned to his good; according to that ſaying of the <hi>Apoſtle, All things worke together to the beſt, to thoſe that loue God.</hi> And ſaith he, doth not that fall make for our good, whereby we become both more humble and more wary?</p>
            <p>This then doth ſerue to confute the fond opinion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of them, that thinke it is not lawfull, either for the Miniſter, or for any other Chriſtian, to iudge any man. As our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſaith. <hi>Iudge not, condemne not.</hi> It is true, a man muſt not iudge raſhly and vnaduiſedly without good ground and ſufficient reaſon. Neither muſt any man iudge finally of another mans eſtate. For that belongeth ſolely and onely to God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16.</note> But as a man may iudge of the goodneſſe or badneſſe of the tree by the fruite that it beareth: ſo by the conuerſation of men we may iudge of their preſent eſtate. If any man ſhall preſume of another mans finall eſtate, whether he ſhall be ſaued or damned, he goeth further then he hath warrant for, and taketh Gods office cut of his hand. A iury, by the euidence that is produced and by due examination of the cauſe, may finde a man guilty: but neither they nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man els, can ſay he ſhall be hanged, becauſe it is in the power of the king to pardon him. In like manner, when we ſee the wicked life and leaude conuerſation of a man, wee may conclude, that for the preſent he is in a damnable caſe: but no man may take vpon him to affirme, that he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16448:23"/>
finally damned, becauſe the Lord may haue mercy vpon him, and pardon his ſinne And therefore, to conclude this point, ſo many as would not be accounted wicked men, let them be admoniſhed to take heede, that they be not workers of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie. If thou wilt make a trade of ſwearing, drinking who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, prophaning the Sabbaoth, &amp;c. it is no breach of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at all, to ſay that thou art a wicked man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From th citie of the Lord.)</hi> This the end of all that went before, namely, why the Prophet would be ſo carefull to <hi>deſtroy the wicked,</hi> and to <hi>cut off the workers of iniquitie,</hi> and that <hi>betimes,</hi> euen becauſe he would preſerue the <hi>citie of the Lord</hi> from the pollution of ſinne By the <hi>citie of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5 35.</note> in this place is meant <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> which is alſo called <hi>The citie of the great King,</hi> becauſe there the Lord appointed a place for the habitation of his name: as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking in the perſon of God, <hi>The Lord hath choſen Zion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>and loued to dwell in it,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This is my reſt for euer, here will I dwell, for I haue dilight therein.</hi> It is called likwiſe the <hi>holy citie,</hi> becauſe it was appointed and conſecrated to holy vſes, to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of true religion, and the ſeruice of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.5.</note> For there was the temple, there was the prieſthood, there was the law and word of God. Now the Prophet promiſeth to haue a ſpeciall care of this place, becauſe it was a type of Gods Church, and the chiefe citie in the Kingdome. From whence wee are taught this inſtruction, that as <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> muſt haue a care to reforme euill euery where: ſo eſpecially, in places that are of greateſt note. Great ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſuch like places, are chiefely to bee looked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. The reaſon is. Firſt, becauſe ſuch places ſtand moſt neede, becauſe there commonly is moſt vngodlineſſe and impietie, by reaſon of the great conſluence that is of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of all nations. Secondly, for example ſake. For more good or hurt redoundeth to the whole land by the example of ſuch places. The <hi>Prophet Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> ſpeaking of the wicked <hi>Prieſts</hi> of his time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.15.</note> ſaid that <hi>From them wickedneſſe was gone forth into, all the land.</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16448:24"/>
As this is true of great perſons, ſo it is true alſo of great pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And this we ſee by too much experience. For doth not <hi>London</hi> furniſh all the land with pride and vanitie? where are all the ſtrange diſguiſes, and monſtrous faſhions of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell inuerted but here? and from hence they are conueied into all the parts of the land. Laſt of all, ſinne is a greater diſgrace to great places then to others, becauſe they haue more meanes to make them good.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.20</note> And therefore our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt</hi> doth more vpbraide thoſe cities wherein he had moſt preached, and where he had wrought moſt of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles then any other place beſides.<note place="margin">21</note> 
               <hi>Wee be to thee Corazin,</hi> ſaith he <hi>wee be to thee Bethſaida: for if the great workes which haue beene done in you, had beene done in Tyrus and Sidon, they would haue repented long agone in ſackechoath and aſhes. And thou Capernaum, which art lifted vp vnto heauen, ſhall be caſt downe into hell, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This being ſo, let the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of this place chiefely be exhorted, to haue a ſpeciall care of reforming ſinne in this great cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, leaſt other places by the example thereof be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened and encouraged in euill. It is the corruption of mans nature, rather to be led by the example of others, then by the precepts and rules of the word of God. And this place is euen as <hi>a citie ſet vpon an hill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14</note> all mens eyes are vpon it. And therefore, if this citie that ſhould be <hi>faithfull become an harlot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Naum.</hi> 3.1</note> if this citie be <hi>a bloody citie, full of lies and robberie,</hi> if <hi>London</hi> be diſordered and wicked, it will be a priuiledge as it were to all other places to doe the like. And therefore, you that are in authority here, labour to purge this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that all the ſtreames in the land may be cleare and pure.</p>
            <p>Thus, as God hath enabled me, I haue handled the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things contained in this text. There is yet another thing worthy our conſideration, which <hi>Caluin</hi> by way of <hi>Allegorie</hi> obſerueth in this place. Which I will briefely adde for a concluſion of all.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> as we know, was a type of our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16448:24"/>
Chriſt.</hi> And as he promiſeth <hi>betimes</hi> or <hi>in the morning to deſtroy all the wicked of the land:</hi> So though <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> doe with patience long ſuffer and endure vngodly perſons: yet there will come a <hi>morning</hi> wherein he will ariſe to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement, and <hi>Shew himſelfe from heauen with his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Angels, in flaming fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>The.</hi> 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to render vengeance on them that know not God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Then <hi>Shall all the wicked be turned to hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>and all the people that forget God.</hi> Where they <hi>Shall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord and from the glory of his power.</hi> And howſoeuer in the conceit of carnall men, the <hi>Lord</hi> may ſeeme to <hi>deferre his comming:</hi> yet in the end, <hi>he will come in a day when they looke not for him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.48 50.51.</note> 
               <hi>and in an houre that they are not aware of, and will cut them in peeces, and gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them their portion with hypocrites, where there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22</note> I will ſhut vp all with that exhortation of <hi>Dauid, O conſider this, ye that forget God, leaſt he teare you in peeces and there be none to deliuer you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
